Guide to the Ladies' Christian Union Records 1850-2001 (Bulk 1858-1960) MS 359
New-York Historical Society
- Series VII: Lists of Boarders and Members of LCU, 1860-1870
  - Subseries 2: Lists of Members of LCU, 1858-1938, undated
    - List of Members of Ladies' Christian Union, 1896-1938 (Box 9, Folder 20)
    - List of Elected Managers of LCU, includes dates of death of individuals, 1858-1934 (Box 9, Folder 21)
    - Address Book of Members, includes individual's religion, 1872-1873 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Address Book of Members, includes individual's religion, 1859-1879 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Address Book of Members, includes denomination and church, undated (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Address Book of Members, includes denomination and church, undated (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Subseries 3: Lists of Members of Band of Prayer, 1870-1882
    The Band of Prayer was a group of the LCU who prayed for each others' petitions. The Band was open to women everywhere, and had members from all over the country and eventually, all over the world. These materials have been digitized and can be viewed here.
    - Lists of Members, 1872-1882 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Lists of Members, undated (Box 10, Folder 6)
- Series VIII: Photographs, [1880-1994], undated
  This series contains photographs of the residents of the LCU, the interiors and exteriors of the homes, and a few pictures of the workers. Many of these photographs are featured in brochures of the LCU. The pictures of the residents include depictions of the girls eating in the dining hall, lounging in the "parlor," reading or watching television, and sitting outside in the garden or playing ping pong. The photographs of the buildings are organized by the name of the home whenever possible. The building photographs do not contain pictures of the residents, jusy pictures of the facades or empty interiors. Unfortunately, many of the interior and exterior shots cannot be identified with a particular home. There are only a few photographs of the administrators and workers within the homes. Dates of most of the photographs are approximate. These materials have been digitized and can be viewed here.
  - Residents in Dining Halls, [1920-1994] (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Residents in Rooms, [1980-1990] (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Residents, Indoor Recreation, [1950-1994] (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Residents, Outdoor Recreation, [1950-1994] (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Residents at Christmas Parties, 1945, 1990, 1993 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Sage House, formerly the Young Women's Home, [1880-1960] (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Hegeman House, formerly the Branch Home, [1920], undated (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Katharine House, 1930, 1932, undated (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Milbank Memorial Home, [1920-1994] (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Rosemary House, undated (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Roberts House, [1920-1980] (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Eva Home, [1900] (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Unidentified Buildings, Interiors, [1990-1994] (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Unidentified Buildings, Interiors, undated (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Unidentified Building, Exteriors, undated (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Unidentified Building, Garden, [1994] (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Unidentified Building, Bathrooms, [1990-1994] (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Unidentified Building, Bathrooms, [1960-1994] (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Photographs of Administrative Timeline of LCU, undated (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Negatives, undated (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Residents (Oversize), [1950-1959] (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Building Exteriors (Oversize), undated (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Building Interiors (Oversize), undated (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Building Interiors (Oversize), undated (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Halftone photomechanical printing blocks used in production of 1950's LCU Brochure, [1950-1955] (Box 13, Folder Object)
- Series IX: Brochures, [1870-1966], undated
  This series contains brochures and circulars generated by the LCU about its homes, services, and devotional work. These materials have been digitzed and can be viewed here.
  - Copies of LCU Brochure, "Where to Live in New York", [1955] (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - Copies of LCU Brochure, "Where to Live in New York", [1955] (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - Brochures for Hegeman House entitled, "Temporary Homes for Women", [1873-1876] (Box 11, Folder 15)
  - Band of Prayer Informational Circulars, 1870-1877 (Box 11, Folder 16)
  - Brochure for Sage House Memorial Library, 1966 (Box 11, Folder 17)
  - General Brochures about LCU, undated (Box 11, Folder 18)
  - Brochure that includes a blank applications for residency and regulations for boarders, undated (Box 11, Folder 19)
  - Circular stating the Order of Exercises for the Devotional Meetings, undated (Box 11, Folder 20)
- Series X: LCU Celebrations and Events, 1868-1966, undated
  This series contains speeches, ephemera, and objects from LCU celebrations and events. These materials have been digitized and can be viewed here.
  - Peter Cooper's Address at the Opening of the Young Women's Home, 1868 (Box 11, Folder 21)
  - Speech re Celebration of Fortieth Anniversary of Rosemary House, 1948 (Box 11, Folder 22)
  - Centennial Address by Joseph Sizoo, D.D., 1959 (Box 11, Folder 23)
  - Programs from 75th and 100th Anniversary Celebrations of LCU, 1932, 1958 (Box 11, Folder 24)
  - Programs for Concerts, 1881, undated (Box 11, Folder 25)
  - Tickets to Annual Meetings and other LCU Events, 1908, 1966 (Box 11, Folder 26)
  - Calendars of Meeting Dates, 1901-1906 (Box 11, Folder 27)
  - Trowel presented to Ella Dunlevy Milbank on the laying of the cornerstone of Katharine House, 1930 (Box 13, Folder Object)
  - Plaque donated to Helen A. Clark Memorial Library at the Sage House, undated (Box 13, Folder Object)
- Series XI: Tributes to LCU Leaders, 1874-1949, undated
  This series contains information relating to the leaders and members of the LCU. Most of the material consists of tributes to LCU members who had recently died. In addition to The Royalty of Faith in box 14, three more copies of the book are housed in the metal LCU box 15. These materials have been digitized and can be viewed here.
  - Tributes to Mrs. Caroline Roberts, [1874] (Box 11, Folder 28)
  - Tributes to Ella Dunlevy Milbank, 1912-1913 (Box 11, Folder 29)
  - Tribute to Mrs. Theodore Schulze, 1949 (Box 11, Folder 30)
  - Tribute to Mrs. S. F. Marsh, 1896 (Box 11, Folder 31)
  - The Royalty of Faith: A Meditation on the Life of Mrs. Marshall O. Roberts, by Joseph P. Thompson (2 copies), undated (Box 14)
  - The Royalty of Faith: A Meditation on the Life of Mrs. Marshall O. Roberts, by Joseph P. Thompson (3 copies), undated (Box 15)
- Series XII: Manuals, 1869-1876
  Scope and Contents
  These materials have been digitized and can be viewed here.
  - Manuals of LCU, 1869-1876 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Band of Prayer Manuals, 1870 (Box 12, Folder 2)
- Series XIII: Articles, 1868-1997, undated
  This series is comprised of various articles written about the houses, boarders, and administrators of the Ladies' Christian Union. The scrapbook contains articles from Christian papers such as the Advocate and Guardian, New York Daily Witness, and Advance. These materials have been digitized and can be viewed here.
  - Magazine and Newspaper Clippings, 1877-1997, undated (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Article, "Residence Clubs" in Glamour, 1947 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Article, "More Than Bed and Board" in Cosmopolitan, 1981 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Scrapbook of Articles, 1868-1883 (Box 12, Folder 6)
- Series XIV: Young Women's Christian Association (YWCA), 1860-1945
  This series contains a small amount of material on the history of the YWCA, which began in 1870 as the Young Ladies' Branch of the Ladies' Christian Union. The material contains some handouts outlining the history of the Association and appeals for funds. Also included is a 1948 pamphlet by Joseph Kamp reporting on the "infiltration" of Communists in the YWCA and accusing the association of disseminating Communist propaganda.
  - Historical Sketches of the YWCA, 1920, 1945 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - "Behind the Lace Curtains of the YWCA" by Joseph Kamp, 1948 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - An Appeal by the "Women's Christian Association", [1860] (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Resolution by the Women's Christian Association re Death of Mrs. Caroline Roberts, [1874] (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Circular by "Young Ladies' Branch" of the Ladies' Christian Union, 1870 (Box 12, Folder 11)
- Series XV: Books, 1911-1932
  This series contains books that appear to have been part of a house library or books left by residents.
  - Rational Typewriting, Typewriting textbook, 1911 (Box 14)
  - Recollections of an Old New Yorker, by Frederick Van Wyck, 1932 (Box 14)